The point plot function you saw previously,
之前介绍的 pointplot 函数
was good for summarizing a quantitative variable against a qualitative variable.
擅长探索数值变量与分类变量的关系
We need a different function for summarizing
我们需要另一个函数来探索
a quantitative variable against a second quantitative variable,
两个数值变量的关系
such as with fuel efficiency by engine displacement.
比如燃油效率和发动机排量
In this case, we'll make use of Matplotlib's error bar function,
这次 我们要用 Matplotlib 的 errorbar 函数
which plots a line between points with an optional setting for adding error bars.
该函数会连点成线 而我们可以选择是否添加误差线
We can set the data X and Y arguments just like we've done before.
像之前一样设置参数 data、x 和 y
Unfortunately, the plot we get out is uninformative.
然而绘制出来的图表并不能提炼出什么信息
All that Matplotlib is doing is connecting each pair of X and Y
Matplotlib 直接把每对 x 和 y 值
values in order as they appear in the data frame without any sorting.
按其在 DataFrame 中出现的先后顺序连接了起来 没有进行合理的排序
A scatter plot is basically this plot,
把这张图的连线去掉
but without any connecting lines and distinct points at each value pair.
只呈现每对值相应的点 就是散点图了
We'll be fine to use error bar if all of our data is sorted by
如果所有数据都按 x 变量进行排序
the X variable and we only have one Y value for each X value.
而且每个 x 值只对应一个 y 值 那我们就可以使用误差线了
So, let's do some work to get a data frame with those qualities.
为此 我们要给 DataFrame 做相应的调整
First of all, I'm going to set bin edges and
首先 设置分组边界和中心点
centers for summarizing the data on the displacement value.
对排量数据进行汇总
I need these center-values so that the points are plotted in their accurate positions.
我要用中心值来准确绘制数据点
I'm leaving out the last value of the bin edges,
就不管分组边界的最后一个值了
since that won't correspond to an actual bin center.
反正没有实际的组中心与之对应
Next, I'll use Panda's cut function to
接着 用 Pandas 的 cut 函数
figure out which bin each data points should be used in.
来确定各数据点对应哪一组
The first argument is the series I'm slicing,
第一个参数是一个切片出来的 Series
the second argument is the set of bins,
第二个参数是分组的集合
and the third argument makes sure that the values that are
第三个参数用于确保等于平均值的值
equal to the mean get included into the bins.
也会包含在组内
Now, I'm going to use groupby to group-by
现在我用 groupby 函数
those displacement bins and then take the mean of points that fall in each bin.
按排量分组聚合 然后取每组数据点的平均值
Finally, we're ready to plot again.
再次绘制图表
Since we're no longer using the original data frame,
因为我们用的不是原始 DataFrame 了
we need to change our arguments.
所以得修改参数
The bin centers are going to go with the X parameter and
用参数 x 设置组中心
the Panda series with the fuel efficiency for the Y parameter.
有关燃油效率的 Pandas Series 则设为参数 y
The line plot looks like this,
所得折线图如图
showing a general decrease in fuel efficiency with engine size.
基本上发动机排量越大 燃油效率越低
There is a gap in the line where there is no data available.
因为有些数据缺失了 所以折线这里出现了空隙
With the error bar function,
使用 errorbar 函数
we can also compute the standard deviation of the fuel efficiencies in
我们还可以计算每一组燃油效率的标准差
each bin and then plot them through the yerr parameter.
并用参数 yerr 将其绘制出来
This plot shows that while the cars with
由图可知
smaller engine sizes have generally higher fuel efficiency,
虽然发动机排量较小的车辆总体上燃油效率较高
there's also a lot more variability in those efficiencies.
但差异性也比较大